Previously,
前情提要
Komi took care of Tadano when he had a cold.
古見同學去只野同學家探病
While caring for him, she held his hand.
在照顧只野同學時 不經意握住他的手
Then Najimi burst in.
此時馴染闖入
-Hey! Tadano, are you alive? -INTRUSION
-嗨！只野同學，還活著嗎？ -（闖入）
Times like this, even if people with social anxiety think,
沒錯，在這種時候有交流障礙症的人
"What should I do? Was I seen?"
會想說“怎麼辦？被看到了啦！”
But they don't have the skills to find out.
而她卻想不出方法來確認此事
FILLED WITH ANXIETY ON THE LAST DAY OF WINTER BREAK
（一想到寒假今天結束便坐立難安）
TRYING TO CALM DOWN
（先嘗試冷靜下來）
MISSION 64 "IT'S JUST A MISUNDERSTANDING."
（任務64 是誤會）
NOT SURE WHY I DID THAT
（自己也搞不懂為什麼會那麼做）
Oh, so that's how it is!
喔，原來如此，是這麼回事啊！
Huh!
是喔！
THAT'S HOW WHAT IS?!
（“是這麼回事”？）
I HAVE TO FIX THE MISUNDERSTANDING!
（總之得先解開誤會！）
"Dear Najimi,
“馴染同學
I want to avoid a misunderstanding.
我希望你別誤會
I had absolutely no ulterior motive.
我當時並沒有任何企圖 也非別有用心
It came from a place of friendship.
純粹是基於朋友間的情誼
He was distressed and I was moved to hold his hand.
看到只野同學受病痛所苦 才會握住他的手
So I did.
僅只如此
I repeat, there was no deeper meaning.
請容我重申一遍，我沒有其他的意圖
I have nothing to be ashamed of.
當時也並非別有居心
This letter is to help you understand…"
為了讓你了解當下的情況 我才寫下這封…”
LOOKS LIKE I'M APOLOGIZING FOR SOMETHING SHAMEFUL!
（怎麼看都像是在對 愧對良心的自己找藉口！）
AH
（驚覺）
I don't know if I really was seen.
說到底根本不確定有沒有被他看到
If I handed over a letter like this…
要是直接給他這封信…
Whoa, you did something shameful?
什麼嘛，妳當時有所企圖啊？
Huh?
是這樣啊？
After all, I just held his hand. Maybe it's not such a big deal!
仔細想想只不過是握住他的手 似乎不算什麼大事
For Komi, it was a big deal.
可是對古見同學而言這可是一件大事
-Good morning! -THE NEXT DAY
-早安！ -（隔天）
SPENT ALL NIGHT WRITING IT
（昨晚熬夜寫好的信）
Ah, so beautiful.
天啊，真美麗
I saw Komi on the first day back!
-開學第一天竟然就能看到古見同學 -我真是幸運！
Komi! Hey-ho!
古見同學！早安，哈囉！
STARTLE
（驚嚇）
Hm? What are you doing?
嗯？妳在做什麼？
TO: NAJIMI OSANA
（給長名馴染同學）
Yay! A love letter from Komi!
好耶！古見同學給了我情書！
WOO
（飛奔）
Good morning, Komi.
早安，古見同學
STARTLE
（驚嚇）
What's wrong?
怎麼了嗎？
Seeing Tadano made her feel more embarrassed than the letter.
發現比起將信交給只野同學 見到他會更加害羞的古見同學
Incidentally, the content of the letter.
順帶一提，信中的內容是…
I WAS JUST TAKING HIS PULSE. SHOKO KOMI
（我只是在給他把脈 古見硝子）
Pulse?
“把脈”？
That morning…
時光稍微倒轉…
-Can you go to school? -Yeah, I'm better.
-可以去學校嗎？ -可以，現在身體好多了
I feel like Komi came over yesterday.
總覺得昨天古見同學好像有來家裡
-I think she did come. -IT'S ALL SO HAZY
-她應該有來才對 -（當時意識矇矓記不清楚）
But I was so sick, it might have been a hallucination.
但當時太過難受了，說不定是幻覺
If it was a hallucination…
如果真的是幻覺…
Thanks for yesterday.
昨天謝謝妳
You helped me feel much better.
多虧妳，我的感冒已經好了
Uh, you came over yesterday, right?
那個，妳昨天有來我家探病對吧？
EW
（厭惡）
So creepy!
太噁心了！
Saying thanks for appearing in a hallucination is too creepy!
擅自產生出這種幻覺後 再道謝的我實在太噁心了！
I think she did come, but I don't have proof.
我想她應該有來，可是我無法確定
You're looking ill again!
哥哥，你臉色還是很差耶
A-Anyway, if she did come I do have to thank her.
總之如果她有來，就要向她道謝
But I can't ask her if she came.
不過我不敢開口問 她到底有沒有來家裡
It's too rude to say I don't remember.
不過說我不記得也顯得很失禮
-I do have evidence that Najimi came. -YOU OWE ME
-馴染倒是有留下來探病的蹤跡 -（明細）
I should ask Najimi.
去問一下馴染好了
-Yay! A love letter from Komi! -WOO
-好耶！古見同學給了我情書！ -（飛奔）
I ran into Komi first.
竟然在問他之前先碰到古見同學
It would be weird to avoid her.
也不好意思避著她
-Good morning, Komi. -STARTLE
-早安，古見同學 -（驚嚇）
STARE
（盯）
S-She's watching me.
總覺得被她盯著看
W-What's wrong?
怎麼了嗎？
HMPH!
（別過頭）
W-What does that reaction mean?
這反應是哪種意思？
Why?
為什麼？
IS YOUR COLD ALRIGHT?
（感冒還好嗎？）
I guess Komi really did…
古見同學果然有來…
No, I accidentally called her, so she knows I was sick.
不對，我昨天打錯電話 她應該知道我感冒的事
Ah, yes, thanks. Much better.
是，我身體好多了
Sorry about yesterday.
昨天真是不好意思
Alright! Now it's not clear if I'm talking about the call
很好！這樣回答她應該就不知道
or when she came and took care of me.
我是在講打錯電話還是探病的事
It works either way.
不管是哪種，聽起來都很自然
Now I'll watch her reaction.
接著觀察古見同學的反應來判斷
NOD
（點頭）
W-Why is she looking away?
為什麼要別過頭？
What should I do? I need more information.
怎麼辦？我需要打探更多情報
Anyway…
話說回來
What did you do… after that?
妳在那之後有做什麼嗎？
AFTER THAT?
（在那之後？）
After that.
在那之後…
50M IN 6.89 SECONDS
（50公尺6.89秒）
Komi?!
古見同學？
W-What's going on?
到底是怎麼回事？
Morning, Tadano!
早安，只野同學！
Oh, Najimi.
啊，馴染
Do you know what Komi was doing yesterday?
你知道昨天古見同學在做什麼嗎？
Oh, Komi?
什麼？古見同學？
I WAS JUST TAKING HIS PULSE. SHOKO KOMI
（我只是在給他把脈 古見硝子）
She was taking your pulse!
她好像是在把脈
Huh? Pulse?
什麼？把脈？
TREMBLE
（顫抖）
WAS TADANO AWAKE?
（只野同學當時醒著？）
The misunderstanding deepens.
誤會不斷加深
MISSION 66 "IT'S JUST A NARCISSIST."
（任務66 是自戀狂）
What is a narcissist?
“自戀狂”一詞
The word comes from a Greek myth about beautiful young Narcissus,
源自於希臘神話中登場的 美少年納西瑟斯
who fell in love with his reflection in a pool of water.
因他愛上水面倒映出的自己 所誕生的名詞
And it's likely…
相信當時…
What's this?
怎麼會這樣呢？
While Narcissus gazed at his own reflection in the pool,
納西瑟斯愛上水面倒影的自己時
he was surely fiddling with his bangs!
肯定也如此把玩過自己的瀏海
I'm just too handsome!
實在太帥了
Naruse is a narcissist.
成瀬同學是自戀狂
My name is Shisuto Naruse.
我的名字叫成瀬詩守斗
I'm the…
我是這部作品的…
handsome protagonist.
型男主角
That's his personal opinion.
這只是他個人的意見
It may differ from the actual premise.
與實際上的設定可能有所偏差
Kometani provides commentary.
米谷同學會幫他加註解
I do love Justice Beaver.
小賈斯頂的歌果然不錯
-POINT #1 -Shows off taste for Western music.
-（自戀狂要點1） -會大肆宣揚自己有聽西洋音樂
-POINT #2 -Bangs his chair.
-（自戀狂要點2） -會搖椅子發出聲音
-POINT #3 -Blows on his bangs.
-（自戀狂要點3） -會吹瀏海
Oh my.
糟糕
I'm drawing attention to myself again.
一個不小心今天又吸引眾人的目光了
-I'm so bad. -Nobody is watching.
-真是我的壞習慣 -沒有人在看
If I must…
沒辦法
I'll give you a little show.
就稍微發點福利吧
Nobody is…
沒有人在…
Hey, is everyone gazing from afar?
喂，大家何必離得這麼遠眺望？
I could allow a quick chat!
要我稍微陪你們聊聊也行！
He's completely alone.
他完全是班上的邊緣人
What are those two always up to?
我之前就在想這兩個人到底在幹嘛
Shy little kittens.
真是一群靦腆的小貓咪
Refers to everyone else as "kittens."
稱自己以外的 不特定多數人為“小貓咪”
Fine.
無妨
I'm so beautiful, there's only one who is worthy to join me.
在這班上只有一個人配得上美麗的我
Yes.
沒錯
Komi is the only one!
只有古見同學一人！
NARUSE'S PERSONAL OPINION.
（純屬他個人的意見）
But school started nine months ago.
不過都入學九個月了
And she hasn't spoken a word to me.
她至今仍未與我攀談
Perhaps Komi has social anxiety?
莫非古見同學有交流障礙症？
He got that one right.
這點倒是說中了
No, not possible.
這怎麼可能
Her beauty is comparable to my own.
她可是擁有與我匹敵的美貌
A flower waiting for a honeybee.
那朵鮮花肯定是在等蜜蜂主動靠近
That's it. I've got no other choice.
若是這樣，那也沒辦法
Just know, my honeybee is huge!
但我的蜜蜂可是很大的
This statement isn't meant to be dirty.
這句話並不是在開黃腔
Hey, Kom--
嗨，古見同…
Hey…
嗨…
Hey, Ko… mi…
嗨，古…見…
SWARM
（蜂擁而上）
-Ko… mi… -MOVING TO A DIFFERENT CLASSROOM
-古…見… -（換教室）
SCIENCE LAB
（理科教室）
What just happened?
剛才的究竟是怎麼回事？
I feel like they were trying to stop Komi from getting to me.
我感受到眾人無論如何 都不希望我靠近古見同學的強烈意志
Oh, I know!
原來是這樣！
They're my fans!
他們是我的粉絲啊！
Everyone came to see me!
所以大家才會湧上來呀！
Oh, my silly fans!
我的那些粉絲真是的！
MENTAL RESET
（再次恢復精神）
There's Komi.
那是古見同學
Now my fans aren't around.
好，現在周圍正好沒有其他粉絲在
It's my chance! Hey, Komi…
機會來了，嗨，古見同…
Another fan?
又是粉絲？
Sorry, we can talk later…
不好意思，晚點再陪妳聊…
Who are you to talk to Komi?
誰准你跟古見同學講話了？
I know your intentions, Naru-boy.
任誰都看得出你的邪念，自戀男
You're totally uncool.
而且你根本就不帥
Too self-absorbed. You should get that checked.
少自我意識過剩了 我建議你先去醫院看看大腦
You're sick if you think you're on Komi's level
光是你稍微以為自己配得上古見同學 就已經病入膏肓了
So cheeky I laughed.
自大到讓人笑死
Wash your sticky hair before you go near her.
先把你噴滿定型液的油頭洗乾淨再說
Baldy baldy baldy…
你這禿頭…
Oh! Komi, wait up!
啊！古見同學，等等我！
Ko… Ugh! What is that?
古…這是什麼？
He continued to try to approach Komi.
之後仍不氣餒地 努力找古見同學攀談的
Baldy… Naruse tried his best.
禿頭成瀬同學
If you want to pass, you must first defeat me!
要是想通過，就先打倒我吧！
-CONCENTRATION GAME -W-What a pain.
-（撲克牌翻翻樂） -好麻煩
THROWING STAR
（手裏劍）
NARUSE, BATTERED.
（身心俱疲的成瀬同學）
The jealousy of my fans is amazing.
粉絲的嫉妒心真強
That's how he is.
他就是這樣的人
Come on. You might love me, but that's taking it too far.
喂，就算是喜歡我 也做得太過火了吧
Well, now I've got to go to the restroom and gaze at my reflection to recover.
傷腦筋，去廁所看看自己的臉 被療癒一下吧
I don't feel well.
不然身體可撐不住
But I'm still popular.
誰叫我這麼受歡迎
FLAP
（掉落）
That's odd.
不對勁
Usually, no matter how unwell I feel,
過去不論身體狀況多差
I recover as soon as I see my own face.
只要看到自己的臉馬上就能恢復
My chest hurts. The world looks faded and dim.
胸口好痛苦 眼前所見的景象都褪去了色彩
Stress.
壓力所致
And as I was saying,
因為這樣
uh, this goes like this,
所以這邊變成這樣…
-Now I see. -And then that is like that…
-我懂了 -最後變成這樣
She's…
她原來…
in love with me.
是喜歡我啊？
Is she looking at me now?
現在也在看我是嗎？
She's not.
並沒有
THE NEXT DAY
（隔天）
Actually, I did.
其實就是今天
W-What?
什麼狀況？
OFFERING TO TRADE NUMBERS
（他想給古見同學 交換手機號碼的機會）
USER QR CODE
（手機QR碼）
TAP
（輕觸）
Huh?
什麼？
Komi didn't understand what she was supposed to do.
不知該如何是好的古見同學
That's only natural.
當然會這樣
He couldn't accept reality,
他無法接受這現實
so he pretended he'd been asking Tadano all along.
最後假裝是打從一開始 就想跟只野同學交換手機號碼
Huh? Me?
什麼？跟我嗎？
He's always like this.
雖然他是這種人
But he's not a bad guy. Go on and trade numbers.
但不是什麼壞人 你就跟他交換號碼吧
Uh, yeah.
什麼？好
Tadano made a new friend!
只野同學的朋友變多了！
Naruse started sending Tadano a selfie a day.
每天收到一張自拍照的只野同學
Alright. Tomorrow we're choosing groups for the field trip.
聽好了，明天要決定校外教學的分組
Yay!
好耶！
I was born to go on field trips!
我就是為了參加校外教學而生的！
That excited?
有這麼興奮？
AFTER SCHOOL
（放學後）
Ah, Kyoto.
天啊，京都
KYOTO
（京都）
A fascinating wonderland where the past and present interweave.
古今交織的迷人樂園
Heh. I can't wait.
嘿，好期待啊
Were you always such a Kyoto fan?
你有這麼喜歡京都？
Tsk tsk tsk.
嘖嘖嘖
Tadano, the thing about travel.
只野同學，所謂的旅行
It isn't where you go, but who you go with!
重點不是去哪，而是跟誰去
Is that so?
這樣啊
But Kyoto's pretty nice.
不過京都確實很棒
-Temples and shrines. -LOVES OLD BUILDINGS
-有很多寺廟跟神社 -（喜歡古色古香的建築）
The five-storied pagoda.
五重塔也不錯
-Huh. -Totally disinterested!
-是喔 -竟然完全沒興趣
Komi, is there somewhere you want to go?
古見同學有想去的地方嗎？
Komi?
古見同學？
SORRY. WHAT IS IT?
（抱歉，你說什麼？）
Um, is there somewhere you want to go?
沒有啦，想問一下 妳有沒有想去的地方
I HOPE WE CAN GO TO THE ARCADE AGAIN.
（想再跟大家一起去電玩中心）
Uh, I meant in Kyoto.
那個，我是說京都啦
I WANT TO SEE GINKAKUJI.
（我想看看銀閣寺）
Oh, very nice!
這樣啊，不錯耶！
Kinkakuji is nice too, but Ginkakuji is elegant.
金閣寺固然漂亮 銀閣寺也充滿韻味呢
The overall harmony, the way the garden completes it…
整體調和得很棒 連同庭園一起觀賞才是最完整…
How old are you?
你是老爺爺嗎？
-SORRY, I'LL BE RIGHT BACK. -Oh, okay!
-（抱歉，我先離席） -啊，好的！
See ya later!
去方便一下吧！
And it's like, was tofu always this good?
然後啊，豆腐超級好吃
They just put it in hot water and it transforms! Kyoto magic!
只不過是用熱水燙過 就有如天壤之別，根本就是京都魔術
Huh.
這樣啊
Komi, where did you go on your junior high field trip?
古見同學國中時的 校外教學是去哪玩？
KYOTO
（去京都）
-Kyoto? -It'll be your second time.
-京都？ -那就是第二次去了呢
Kyoto's fun every time though.
不過京都去幾次都不會膩
It's Kyoto after all!
畢竟是那個京都嘛
Why are you so keen on Kyoto?
你也太推崇京都了吧，是怎樣？
Anyway, I'm quintuple-booked after this.
那我接下來還有五場邀約要去
Q-Quin?
五？
-What? -Byeee!
-什麼意思？ -拜拜囉！
Shall we go?
我們走吧
I'm looking forward to the field trip.
真期待校外教學啊
Najimi has over 100,000 friends in Kyoto.
聽馴染說他在京都有 超過十萬個朋友呢
What does that even mean?
完全聽不懂他在胡扯什麼對吧？
Uh…
那個…
Are you alright?
妳還好嗎？
WHAT DO YOU MEAN?
（什麼意思？）
Oh, uh.
啊，沒有啦
You just seem a little down today.
妳今天好像沒什麼精神
IT'S ALRIGHT. I'M FINE.
（請不必擔心，我很好）
Well that's good then.
那就好
But if something is bothering you, you can tell me anytime.
不過如果有什麼擔心的事 隨時都能找我談喔
I don't know if I can help or not.
雖然不知道我能不能幫上妳的忙
But it might help you feel better talking about it.
但有些事光是說出來 心裡就會舒坦不少
Okay, I'm going this way.
那我要往這邊走
Take care on your way home.
回去路上小心喔
See you tomorrow.
明天見
-VIBRATION -Whoa!
-（震動聲） -哇！
-KOMI -Komi?
-（古見硝子） -古見同學？
Yes, hello?
喂？妳好
Komi?
古見同學？
Um…
那個…
Yes?
怎麼了？
I-I'm sorry.
對不起
Just now, I…
剛才我…
I told a lie.
說謊了
Actually…
其實…
I have never been to Kyoto.
我沒去過京都
Take your time.
慢慢說沒關係
In junior high,
我在唸國中時
we chose groups for the field trip.
有一天要為校外教學分組
And then,
那時候
I was the only one who got left out.
只有我一個人多了出來
Naturally.
這也是理所當然的
I-I didn't have anyone close enough to call a friend.
畢竟我在班上沒有熟識到 能稱得上是朋友的同學
And at that time,
因為當時的我
I didn't have a way to communicate.
不懂得該如何表達自己的意見
Naturally.
所以當然會那樣
Then they started playing rock paper scissors.
最後大家開始猜拳
I joined the group that was left.
我被分入唯一有缺人的組別
The faces of the people in my group…
當時組員的臉…
I…
我…
couldn't even look at them.
根本不敢看他們
I thought they were surely disappointed to be stuck with me.
有我這個多出來的人加入 他們一定非常失望
They'd made this group of friends.
畢竟難得跟要好的朋友分到同一組
Or maybe they didn't care at all.
或許他們根本就對我毫無興趣
I would have been happier with that.
如果是那樣我還比較開心
Maybe they welcomed me with smiles.
說不定，他們其實是用笑臉歡迎我
But…
可是…
I just couldn't…
我卻連頭都…
raise my head to look.
不敢抬起來
On the day of the field trip, I didn't go.
校外教學當天，我沒有去
I'm scared.
我好怕
But now you have friends.
不過妳現在有朋友啊
Yes.
是的
But everyone has other people they're closer to.
但是大家肯定都有更要好的朋友
F-Friends who are more cheerful and easier to talk to.
有比我更加開朗、更好交談的朋友
But you've got me!
可是妳還有我啊！
And Najimi!
還有馴染！
CAUTIOUS TADANO
（臨陣退縮的只野同學）
It's groups of three, separated into boys and girls.
這次聽說是男女分開，三人一組
TADANO = MALE NAJIMI = UNCLEAR
（只野同學，男生 馴染，性別不明）
I-I'm sorry.
對不起
That's all I wanted to say.
只是這樣而已
Thank you very much for listening to…
謝謝你願意聽我說…
Right.
這樣啊
Well, if that's the case, let's both skip out. On the field trip.
如果事情真的演變成那樣 我們就一起在校外教學當天請假吧
Huh? Uh, that's…
什麼？可是…
not okay.
不行
I mean, I appreciate the thought.
我是說，你的這份心意我很高興
But I know you're really looking forward to the field trip.
可是只野同學那麼期待校外教學
In that case, let's go by ourselves! To Kyoto.
不然我們倆一起去京都吧
Heh. Just kidding.
開玩笑的
-CLICK -She hung up!
-（掛斷） -她掛電話了！
Uh, Komi?
那個，古見同學
It was a joke! A joke!
剛才那是開玩笑的！
I-It's alright.
沒關係
I know.
我知道
-Really? -SUDDENLY EMBARRASSED
-真的嗎？ -（現在才開始害羞）
Um… Thank you.
那個，真的很謝謝你
I feel much better now.
我感覺心裡輕鬆了不少
Oh, in that case, I'm glad.
這樣啊，那真是太好了
And the field trip…
那個，校外教學…
I can't wait.
我很期待
Yes.
是啊
Me too!
我也很期待！
When a person has extreme social anxiety,
所謂的“交流障礙症” 是指不擅長和人交流的一種症狀
they struggle to communicate with others.
或是指有這種症狀的人
It'll be alright.
不要緊的
Is everyone here?
大家都到了嗎？
We're going to choose groups for the field trip.
那來為校外教學分組吧
Komi! Let's make a group!
古見同學，跟我一組吧！
Bear in mind,
不過需要注意的是
they only struggle to form connections.
這些人只是不擅長社交
It doesn't mean they don't want to.
但並不表示他們不想和別人有往來
LOTTERY
（抽籤）
I figured that would happen, so I made a lottery.
我早就料到會變這樣 所以用抽籤決定
What will happen to Komi?
古見同學將何去何從？
Find out next time, on the field trip episode!
將在下一集的校外教學篇分曉！
Subtitle translation by: Claire Tanaka
字幕翻譯：蔡柏頤